and I ended up right here in Singapore five weeks later, considerably less jet-lagged than I am right now. And it was a revelation. We traveled through five seas, two oceans, nine ports, and I learned a lot about shipping. And one of the first things that surprised me when I got on board Kendal was, where are all the people? I have friends in the Navy who tell me they sail with 1,000 sailors at a time, but on Kendal there were only 21 crew. Now that's because shipping is very efficient. Containerization has made it very efficient. Ships have automation now. They can operate with small crews. But it also means that, in the words of a port chaplain I once met, the average seafarer you're going to find on a container ship is either tired or exhausted, because the pace of modern shipping is quite punishing for what the shipping calls its human element, a strange phrase which they don't seem to realize sounds a little bit inhuman. So most seafarers now working on container ships often have less than two hours in port at a time. They don't have time to relax. They're at sea for months at a time, and even when they're on board, they don't have access to what a five-year-old would take for granted, the Internet. And another thing that surprised me when I got on board Kendal was who I was sitting next to -- Not the queen; I can't imagine why they put me underneath her portrait -- But around that dining table in the officer's saloon, I was sitting next to a Burmese guy, I was opposite a Romanian, a Moldavian, an Indian. On the next table was a Chinese guy, and in the crew room, it was entirely Filipinos. So that was a normal working ship. Now how is that possible? Because the biggest dramatic change in shipping over the last 60 years, when most of the general public stopped noticing it, was something called an open registry, or a flag of convenience. Ships can now fly the flag of any nation that provides a flag registry. You can get a flag from the landlocked nation of Bolivia, or Mongolia, or North Korea, though that's not very popular. (Laughter) So we have these very multinational, global, mobile crews on ships. And that was a surprise to me. And when we got to pirate waters, down the Bab-el-Mandeb strait and into the Indian Ocean, the ship changed. And that was also shocking, because suddenly, I realized, as the captain said to me, that I had been crazy to choose to go through pirate waters on a container ship. We were no longer allowed on deck. There were double pirate watches. And at that time, there were those 544 seafarers being held hostage, and some of them were held hostage for years because of the nature of shipping and the flag of convenience. Not all of them, but some of them were, because for the minority of unscrupulous ship owners, it can be easy to hide behind the anonymity offered by some flags of convenience. What else does our sea blindness mask? Well, if you go out to sea on a ship or on a cruise ship, and look up to the funnel, you'll see very black smoke. And that's because shipping has very tight margins, and they want cheap fuel, so they use something called bunker fuel, which was described to me by someone in the tanker industry as the dregs of the refinery, or just one step up from asphalt. And shipping is the greenest method of transport. In terms of carbon emissions per ton per mile, it emits about a thousandth of aviation and about a tenth of trucking. But it's not benign, because there's so much of it. So shipping emissions are about three to four percent, almost the same as aviation's. And if you put shipping emissions on a list of the countries' carbon emissions, it would come in about sixth, somewhere near Germany. It was calculated in 2009 that the 15 largest ships pollute in terms of particles and soot and noxious gases as much as all the cars in the world. And the good news is that people are now talking about sustainable shipping. There are interesting initiatives going on. But why has it taken so long? When are we going to start talking and thinking about shipping miles as well as air miles? I also traveled to Cape Cod to look at the plight of the North Atlantic right whale, because this to me was one of the most surprising things about my time at sea, and what it made me think about. We know about man's impact on the ocean in terms of fishing and overfishing, but we don't really know much about what's happening underneath the water. And in fact, shipping has a role to play here, because shipping noise has contributed to damaging the acoustic habitats of ocean creatures. Light doesn't penetrate beneath the surface of the water, so ocean creatures like whales and dolphins and even 800 species of fish communicate by sound. And a North Atlantic right whale can transmit across hundreds of miles. A humpback can transmit a sound across a whole ocean. But a supertanker can also be heard coming across a whole ocean, and because the noise that propellers make underwater is sometimes at the same frequency that whales use, then it can damage their acoustic habitat, and they need this for breeding, for finding feeding grounds, for finding mates. And the acoustic habitat of the North Atlantic right whale has been reduced by up to 90 percent. But there are no laws governing acoustic pollution yet. And when I arrived in Singapore, and I apologize for this, but I didn't want to get off my ship. I'd really loved being on board Kendal. I'd been well treated by the crew, I'd had a garrulous and entertaining captain, and I would happily have signed up for another five weeks, something that the captain also said I was crazy to think about. But I wasn't there for nine months at a time like the Filipino seafarers, who, when I asked them to describe their job to me, called it "dollar for homesickness." They had good salaries, but theirs is still an isolating and difficult life in a dangerous and often difficult element. But when I get to this part, I'm in two minds, because I want to salute those seafarers who bring us 90 percent of everything and get very little thanks or recognition for it. I want to salute the 100,000 ships that are at sea that are doing that work, coming in and out every day, bringing us what we need. But I also want to see shipping, and us, the general public, who know so little about it, to have a bit more scrutiny, to be a bit more transparent, to have 90 percent transparency. Because I think we could all benefit from doing something very simple, which is learning to see the sea. Thank you. (Applause)
y terminé justo aquí en Singapur, 5 semanas después, mucho menos descompensada que ahora. Y fue una revelación. Navegamos 5 mares, 2 océanos, 9 puertos y aprendí mucho sobre el transporte. Y una de las primeras cosas que me sorprendieron cuando llegué a bordo del Kendal fue, ¿dónde está la gente? Tengo amigos en la Armada que me dicen que viajan con 1000 marineros a la vez, pero en el Kendal hay solo 21 tripulantes. Se debe a que el transporte marítimo es muy eficiente. El uso de contenedores ha hecho que sea muy eficiente. Hoy las naves están automatizadas. Pueden operar con tripulaciones pequeñas. Pero eso también significa que, en palabras de un capellán de puerto que conocí una vez, el marinero medio que encontrarán en un barco de contenedores o está cansado o agotado, porque el ritmo del transporte moderno es bastante agotador para lo que en el transporte se llama su "elemento humano", una frase extraña que no parecen advertir que suena un poco inhumana. La mayoría de los marineros que trabajan en barcos de contenedores a menudo pasan menos de 2 horas en el puerto. No tienen tiempo para relajarse. Están en el mar durante meses, e incluso cuando están a bordo, no tienen acceso a lo que un niño de 5 años daría por descontado, Internet. Otra cosa que me sorprendió a bordo del Kendal fueron mis compañeros —no la reina, no sé por qué me pusieron debajo de su retrato—. Alrededor de la mesa de comedor del salón de oficiales estaba sentada al lado de un birmano, y frente a un rumano, un moldavo, un indio. En la otra mesa había un chino, y en la sala de la tripulación, todos eran filipinos. Era una nave normal de trabajo. ¿Cómo es posible? Debido a los drásticos cambios que experimentó el transporte en los últimos 60 años, algo que pasó inadvertido para el público fue el llamado "registro abierto", o "bandera de conveniencia". Los barcos pueden llevar la bandera de cualquier nación que provea un registro de bandera. Pueden conseguir bandera de una nación sin salida al mar como Bolivia, Mongolia o Corea del Norte, aunque no sea muy popular. (Risas) Por eso tenemos esos barcos multinacionales mundiales, con tripulación móvil. Y eso me sorprendió. Y cuando llegamos a aguas piratas, en el estrecho de Bab-el-Mandeb y en el Océano Índico, el barco cambió. Y eso también fue sorprendente, porque, de repente, me di cuenta, cuando me lo dijo el capitán, de que fue una locura eso de entrar en aguas piratas en un barco de contenedores. Ya no podíamos permanecer en cubierta. Había 2 turnos de guardia. En ese momento habían secuestrado a esos 544 marineros, y algunos fueron tomados como rehenes durante años por la naturaleza del transporte y la bandera de conveniencia. No todos, pero algunos lo eran, porque para una minoría de propietarios de buques inescrupulosos, puede ser fácil ocultarse detrás del anonimato que ofrecen algunas banderas de conveniencia. ¿Qué más oculta nuestra ignorancia sobre el mar? Bueno, si salen al mar en un barco o en un crucero, y miran la chimenea, verán un humo muy negro. Y eso se debe a que los barcos tienen márgenes muy estrechos y quieren combustible barato, por eso usan algo llamado fuelóleo que me describieron en el sector petrolero como la escoria de la refinería, solo un paso encima del asfalto. Y el transporte marítimo es el método más ecológico. En materia de emisiones de carbono emite una milésima parte respecto de la aviación y cerca de un décimo del transporte terrestre. Pero no es benigno, porque hay mucho transporte marítimo. Las emisiones del transporte marítimo son del 3 % al 4 %, casi igual que la aviación. Y si ponen las emisiones del transporte marítimo en una lista con las emisiones de carbono por países, estaría en 6° lugar, cerca de Alemania. Se calculó en 2009 que los 15 barcos más grandes contaminan en términos de partículas, hollín y gases nocivos tanto como todos los autos del mundo. Y la buena noticia es que la gente está hablando de un transporte marítimo sustentable. Hay iniciativas interesantes. Pero ¿por qué ha demorado tanto? ¿Cuándo empezaremos a hablar y pensar en las millas marítimas, al igual que en las millas aéreas? También viajé a Cape Cod para ver la difícil situación de la ballena franca del Atlántico Norte, porque esto para mí fue una de las cosas más sorprendentes del tiempo que pasé en el mar, y algo que me ha hecho reflexionar. Conocemos el impacto del hombre sobre el océano en materia de pesca y sobrepesca, pero no sabemos mucho sobre lo que está sucediendo bajo el agua. De hecho, el transporte marítimo juega un papel importante porque su ruido ha contribuido a dañar los hábitats acústicos de las criaturas del océano. La luz no penetra bajo la superficie del agua, por eso los animales marinos como las ballenas, los delfines y 800 especies de peces se comunican con el sonido. Y una ballena franca del Atlántico Norte puede transmitir a través de cientos de kilómetros. La jorobada puede transmitir un sonido por todo el océano. Pero un superpetrolero también puede ser escuchado en todo el océano, y como el ruido que hacen las hélices bajo el agua a veces tiene la misma frecuencia que usan las ballenas, entonces pueden dañar su hábitat acústico, el cual necesitan para reproducirse, para encontrar alimentos, para encontrar pareja. Y el hábitat acústico de la ballena franca del Atlántico Norte se ha reducido en un 90 %. Pero aún no hay leyes que regulen la contaminación acústica. Y cuando llegué a Singapur, pido disculpas por esto, pero no quería bajar de mi barco. Me encantó estar a bordo del Kendal. La tripulación me trató muy bien, el capitán era locuaz y entretenido, y con gusto habría firmado por otras 5 semanas. También por esto el capitán dijo que estaba loca de solo pensarlo. Pero no estaba allí 9 meses por vez como los marinos filipinos, que, cuando les pedí que me describieran su trabajo, dijeron "dinero por nostalgia". Tenían buenos salarios, pero sus vidas siguen siendo aisladas y difíciles en un ambiente peligroso y a menudo difícil. Pero cuando llego a esta parte, siento una ambigüedad, porque quiero saludar a esos marineros que nos dan el 90 % de todo y a cambio reciben muy poco reconocimiento. Quiero saludar a los 100 000 barcos que están en altamar haciendo ese trabajo, yendo y viniendo cada día, trayéndonos lo que necesitamos. Pero también quiero que el transporte marítimo y nosotros, el público, que sabemos muy poco de esto, controlemos un poco más, que sea un poco más transparente, que tenga un 90 % de transparencia. Porque creo que todos podríamos beneficiarnos de hacer algo muy simple, que es aprender a ver el mar. Gracias. (Aplausos)